<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd at the Cathedral Church of Worcester upon the thanksgiving-day, April 16, 1696 by W. Talbot ...</title>
            <author>Talbot, William, 1658 or 9-1730.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62602</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T124</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9963</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13770496</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13770496</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101746</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62602)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101746)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 852:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd at the Cathedral Church of Worcester upon the thanksgiving-day, April 16, 1696 by W. Talbot ...</title>
                  <author>Talbot, William, 1658 or 9-1730.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>28 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for T. Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Publish'd at the request of the mayor and alderman of that city."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXIV, 6-8 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101746:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101746:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd at the Cathedral Church of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> Upon the <hi>
                  <hi>Thankſgiving Day,</hi> April</hi> 16. 1696.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. TALBOT,</hi> D. D. and Dean of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſh'd at the Requeſt of the Mayor and Aldermen of that City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>T. Bennet,</hi> at the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101746:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101746:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful <hi>Nicholas Fayting,</hi> Eſq; Mayor, and the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipful the Aldermen of the City of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE general Joy and Thankfulneſs which have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd throughout the Kingdom, upon the diſcovery and defeat of the late Deſigns of <hi>France</hi> againſt Us, make me hope that the Eyes of this People, which ſome have been ſo buſie to put out, by all the Duſt they could raiſe, are at laſt clear'd; and that many well-meaning Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, who have been miſled by the Cunning of ſuch as lie in wait to deceive, do now begin to ſee that after all the pretences of Honour on the other ſide the Water, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience on this, the Queſtion is come to this ſhort Iſſue, Whether we will live like a Free-People under our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws and Government which have been ſo bravely aſſerted by our Anceſtors, and enjoy our Reform'd Religion, which has been ſeal'd with the Blood of Martyrs, of our Spiritual Fathers and Brethren in <hi>Chriſt;</hi> or, Exchange theſe for a <hi>French</hi> Servitude and Papal Bondage, and bring a Yoke upon our ſelves and Poſterity, which neither we nor our Fathers have been able to bear?</p>
            <p>This You and your Worthy Citizens were certainly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of, when upon the late <hi>Thankſgiving-Day</hi> for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance of His Majeſty and theſe Kingdoms from the deſigned Aſſaſſination and Invaſion You appear'd in ſuch Numbers in the Houſe of God, and expreſt your reſpect to it in ſuch Inſtances as have ſcarcely been parallell'd, upon any occaſion, in this place.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:101746:3"/>
            <p>I heartily wiſh, That my Health and Leiſure would have permitted me to have made that part of the Solemnity that fell to my ſhare of a Piece with the others; and that when all the reſt deſerv'd to be ſet in as bright a Light as that with which You illuminated your Streets upon the Evening of that Joyful Day, it only might not have wanted a Veil to cover it.</p>
            <p>But, however needful it may be, I am ſure I muſt not offer at any Apology for making it publick: None can be made on my part, but what may be anſwer'd in thoſe words of St. <hi>Peter</hi> to <hi>Ananias, While it remain'd with thee was it not thine own?</hi> And as to You, Gentlemen, Now it is yours (tho' You may wiſh that I had made ſuch a return to your Commands as the Elder Brother did to thoſe of his Father in the Goſpel, who ſaid, <hi>Sir, I go, and did not,</hi> rather than with the ſecond, profeſt my unwillingneſs to comply, and afterwards repented and did it) You muſt be contented to account for it, to take it wholly upon your ſelves, and not expect that I ſhould ſay one word for it, for that would be unwarily to intitle my ſelf to its Defence, when I can ſo fairly rid my hands of it, and lay it at your Doors.</p>
            <p>If any of thoſe good Ends ſhall be ſerved by Printing it, which You ſpoke of when You honoured me with a Viſit the Day after it was Preach'd, I ſhall think it but reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable that the acknowledgments thereof ſhould be made only to You, who must bear all the ill Conſequences of it, as having commanded it from me by your Authority, which I do own is very great over,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Worceſter, <date>Apr. 20. 1696.</date>
                  </hi>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Gentlemen, Your moſt Obedient, and Faithful Humble Servant,</hi> W. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:101746:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. CXXIV. 6, 7, 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Bleſſed be the Lord, who hath not given us as a Prey to their Teeth.</p>
                  <p>Our Soul is eſcaped as a Bird out of the Snare of the Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; the Snare is broken, and we are eſcaped.</p>
                  <p>Our help is in the Name of the Lord, who made Heaven and Earth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>The former Part of the Pſalm is thus:
<q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If it had not been the Lord who was on our ſide, now may</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſay:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>If it had not been the Lord who was on our ſide, when Men roſe up against us:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then they had ſwallowed us up quick, when their wrath was kindled against us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then the Waters had overwhelmed us, the Stream had gone over our Soul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Then the proud Waters had gone over our Souls.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Bleſſed,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>THE Title of this Pſalm ſhews the Author of it to be King <hi>David,</hi> and the occaſion of his compoſing it, was certainly ſome ſignal Deliverance either Perſonal or National, which God had beſtow'd upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or his People.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:101746:4"/>
            <p>Whether it were his Deliverance from the ſeveral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns and Attempts upon his Life, of his Father-in-Law King <hi>Saul,</hi> or from the Conſpiracy and Inſurrection of his Son <hi>Abſalom,</hi> or from the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> who came up to ſeek him upon their hearing that he was anointed King over <hi>Iſrael</hi> in <hi>Hebron,</hi> or from the <hi>Ammonites</hi> afterwards with their hired Succours, the <hi>Syrians,</hi> or whatever the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Mercy was, that the Royal Prophet had an Eye to when he made this Euchariſtical Song, 'tis moſt admitably contrived and fitted for the Uſe of any Nation or People, profeſſing God's true Religion, upon any eminent Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of themſelves, or their Prince, from the wicked Deſigns of the Enemies thereof.</p>
            <p>I ſay of themſelves or their Prince: For <hi>David</hi> here makes this grateful Recognition of the Divine Goodneſs in the Name of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as if his People had been in great danger, and very narrowly eſcaped; when yet, according to good Commentators, 'twas a perſonal Deliverance from a Deſign againſt himſelf that he here commemorates; and indeed not without Reaſon, for the Head and the Body-politick are very nearly related, what touches the one muſt affect the other, and if when one Member ſuffers another Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſuffers with it, when the Head is hurt the whole Body muſt ſympathize with it: I ſpeak of ſuch a Head as has that tender Care for the Members which that relation calls for, that looks upon himſelf as exalted above them, only that he may the better watch over them, and more eſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually provide for the Security and Common Good of the whole; that is a true Father of his Country, and treats his Subjects not as Slaves but Children; that is a <hi>good Shepherd, and feeds his People according to the Integrity of his heart, and guides them by the Skillfulneſs of his hand,</hi> as was ſaid of <hi>David,</hi> he does not defraud them of any thing that is their due, much leſs does he butcher and make havock of them; no, that is the Character of the Robber, who <hi>climbs into the Skeepfold only to ſteal, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:101746:4"/>kill, and deſtroy:</hi> The good Shepherd is as careful of the Lives of his Sheep as of his own; nay, ſo much more ſo, that when the Wolf comes he leaves not the Sheep, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes himſelf in their Defence; and rather than that Beaſt of Prey ſhould catch, and ſcatter, and tear his Flock, he ventures his own Life for them, proving himſelf thereby to be no <hi>Thief</hi> or <hi>Hireling,</hi> but the <hi>true Shepherd, whoſe own the Sheep are:</hi> He leads them with Care and Tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he feeds them with Prudence and Kindneſs, and ſights for them with Zeal and Courage: Such a Prince as conſiders and endeavours to anſwer the End of the Inſtitution of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the Good of Mankind, that is join'd with his Subjects in the ſame common Intereſts, both Civil and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, that has no baſe Deſigns of Ambition, Avarice, or Cruelty, no unworthy private Ends to ſerve, but thinks he then only conſults his own Advantage when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motes the Good of the whole, that is no Perſecutor of his Subjects for their adherence to the true Religion, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes the ſame Faith and joins in the ſame Communion with them. In ſhort, that is a juſt Guardian of their Civil Rights and Liberties, and a zealous Defender of their Faith and Religion; ſuch a one is ſo intimately united to his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that he is in the Scripture Language <hi>the Breath of their Noſtrils,</hi> and to Aſſaſſinate him is to Maſſacre a Kingdom; and therefore when <hi>David was delivered from the hurtful Sword of his Enemies,</hi> well might all <hi>Iſrael ſay, Bleſſed be the Lord who has not given us over as a Prey to their Teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whether this Pſalm was at firſt made upon occaſion of a perſonal Deliverance of the King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or not, is not certain; but this is, that it has been look'd upon, and uſed both by the Jewiſh and Chriſtian Church as a proper Hymn of Praiſe to God for National Mercies and Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances.</p>
            <p>Thus amongſt the Jews, the Levites were appointed to ſing it after their Return from their Captivity in <hi>Babylon;</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:101746:5"/>and thus our Church has order'd it to be ſung or ſaid for the Office for the Fifth of <hi>November,</hi> which we obſerve yearly in remembrance of our Deliverance from the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of our Enemies of <hi>Babylon</hi> Myſtical; and ſhe has ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it likewiſe in the Evening Service for this Day, which we are commanded by Authority to obſerve as a Day of Publick Thankſgiving to Almighty God for our late wonderful Deliverance from the no leſs barbarous and bloody Deſigns of the ſame ſort of Enemies, the ſame I mean as to the Principles and Religion they profeſs; for I would fain hope that not many of any other Communion were engaged in, or privy to the blackeſt part of this vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lainous Conſpiracy, that few that call themſelves Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants could join with Papiſts in their worſt Doctrines and Practices, or will ever rob that Church of her peculiar Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and privilege of Aſſaſſinating Princes, of Conſecrating Daggers for their Murder, and Canonizing the villainous Hands that imploy'd them.</p>
            <p>And how reaſonably this Pſalm makes a part of this Day's Service will appear,</p>
            <p n="1">I. By conſidering the two general Parts of it.
<list>
                  <item>The former whereof gives an Account of a great De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance vouchſafed by God to <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>The latter contains the Returns which <hi>Iſrael</hi> made to God for it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. By taking a View of the occaſion of our preſent Meeting; and if our Deliverance be as great as that of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s, 'twill be but fit that we ſhould join with them in their Returns to God, and make the ſame Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of it.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101746:5"/>
            <p>Firſt, Let us conſider <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Deliverance. I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſaid, 'tis uncertain what particular occurrence the Pſalmiſt referrs to, and therefore ſhall only take notice of thoſe general Accounts which we have in this Pſalm of the Enemies that were conſpiring againſt them, the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief they intended, the probability and nearneſs of their Succeſs, with the happy defeat of them, and reſcue of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by the ſeaſonable interpoſition of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>As for the Enemies that were conſpiring againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the 3d Verſe tells us, they were ſuch <hi>whoſe Wrath was kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dled againſt them;</hi> they were, it ſhould ſeem, highly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed by ſome Provocations which they had received, which ſo heared them, their Blood boiled up within them, and nothing could allay the Ferment but the letting out that of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s; they were ſpurr'd on by Rage and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, and violently bent to wreak their Fury and Malice upon them by all the Methods they could put in practice.</p>
            <p>But Anger without Power hurts no body but the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable Subject of it; but alas theſe Men's Power was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to their Rage; they are repreſented, <hi>V.</hi> 4. by <hi>Waters,</hi> which may denote how numerous they were, a vaſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flux or mighty Collection of them; and at the end of that Verſe, by <hi>Streams or Torrents,</hi> violent Interruptions, which bear down all before them; and at the 5th by <hi>proud Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> or, as it is in the other Tranſlation, <hi>deep Waters of the proud,</hi> ſo that there was no wading through them, nor ſtanding againſt them, the Stream was ſo rapid and the Waters ſwoln ſo much above their depth.</p>
            <p>The Miſchief they intended againſt them, was no leſs than their utter ruine, they were for <hi>overwhelming</hi> or <hi>ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing them up,</hi> as we may read in the 3d and 4th Verſes, for making a full end of them, <hi>rooting them out, that the Name of Iſrael might be had no more in remembrance;</hi> and this not leiſurely, or by degrees, but all of a ſudden, they
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101746:6"/>would ſwallow them up <hi>raw or quick,</hi> either as ſome hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Beaſt does his Prey, or as the Sea did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt, and to this end they <hi>roſe up againſt them, V.</hi> 2. and to make ſure work of it, added cunning to their ſtrength, <hi>V.</hi> 7. they laid Snares or Grins for them, attempted them both by open Violence and Secret Treachery.</p>
            <p>And ſo near were they to accompliſh their Ends upon them, that they had as 'twere ſeized their Prey, and were poſſeſs'd of their Game, the rapacious Wolves had got the poor Lambs into their Clutches, and they had no power to reſiſt or reſcue themſelves; they were like ſilly Birds taken in the Nets or Springs of the Fowler, they had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtrength to break them, nor Skill to extricate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of them, the more they flutter'd the more they were entangled, the more they ſtrove, the faſter the Grin held them.</p>
            <p>This briefly was <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s Caſe, their Enemies were mighty, and raged horribly, they were unmoveably re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon their utter Deſtruction, they wanted neither Policy nor Power to effect it; they had proceeded ſo far, and were ſo near doing it, that no humane Means or Power could have prevented or oppoſed them.</p>
            <p>But then God interpoſed, and then indeed the Scene was wonderfully chang'd. How ſure ſoever their Enemies thought themſelves in triumphing in their Overthrow and Extinction, yet the Advantage was plainly then on <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s ſide; for it <hi>was God that was on their ſide, and they were but Men that roſe up againſt them;</hi> and all the Cunning and Power of Men, when oppoſed to the Divine Wiſdom and Strength, is but meer Folly and Weakneſs: He can make the Counſels of the Wiſe of none effect, and take the Crafty in their own Wilineſs: He can baſſle all the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts of the Mighty, and turn their own Forces upon themſelves: And here he broke the <hi>Jaw-bone of the Lyons, and delivered the Prey out of their teeth; he broke the Snare of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodly, and let the oppreſſed Captive go
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101746:6"/>free.</hi> Great Reaſon therefore had <hi>Iſrael</hi> for ſuch a mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Eſcape, to make theſe Acknowledgments and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to the Author of it, which we here ſee they did, namely,</p>
            <p n="1">1. To aſcribe their Deliverance wholly to God, as the doing of that <hi>right hand</hi> only, <hi>which bringeth mighty things to paſs: If the Lord himſelf had not been on our ſide, we had been ſwallowed up quick, and the Stream had gone over our Souls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To give him the Praiſe due unto his Name for it: <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord who has not given us over as a Prey to their Teeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. And Laſtly, to declare their Confidence in him, and intire reliance upon his Power and Goodneſs for the time to come: <hi>Our Help standeth in the Name of the Lord who hath made Heaven and Earth.</hi> That God who mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted his Power and Goodneſs, by Creating the World out of Nothing by a Word of his Mouth, and giving Being to all the Creatures in it, has as evidently ſhewn forth thoſe glorious Attributes in our ſtrange Preſervation and Reſcue out of the Hands of our formidable and implacable Enemies; there will we therefore place our Confidence, not <hi>fearing what Man can do unto us:</hi> On God we will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend, <hi>He only is our Rock and Salvation, our Defence and Refuge, through him we ſhall do valiantly, and he ſhall tread down our Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that ſhort Account of this Pſalm, of <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent Danger, their wonderful Deliverance from it, and grateful Behaviour thereupon.</p>
            <p>I proceed now to take a View of our own Caſe: It will not, I ſuppoſe, be expected that I ſhould go about to prove the Plot, That there has been a moſt Horrid and Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Deſign on-foot againſt the Life of our King, and the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101746:7"/>Laws, and Religion of this Kingdom. After the volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Depoſitions of ſeveral that were to be concerned in it; and theſe confirm'd from abroad by the viſible Prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations that were made on the <hi>French</hi> Coaſts for a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent upon us; a great number of their Forces drawn down thither, and Veſſels ready to bring them over, when the Signal, an Account of the Dreadful Blow, ſhould be given them; the mighty boaſt of their great Deſign and Confidence of Succeſs, which were expreſs'd in Letters from ſome of the firſt Quality in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and the Harangues of their Miniſters at other Courts: This confirm'd alſo at home by the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of thoſe who have been Convicted and Executed here, who have all own'd the ſhares they were to have had in it upon their Deaths, and ſome gloried in it: While a Papiſt at his Execution looks back with regret upon the part he was to have acted in the bloody Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedy, as a Crime he was led into by his own Raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Paſſion, as a Wickedneſs which he repents of, and for the puniſhment of which particularly he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges he was brought to ſuffer Death, by the juſt Hand of God, our Proteſtant Conſpirators, to the reproach (I hope not of our Holy Religion, which I am ſure is far e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from countenancing ſuch things, but of) their wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Guides, boaſt of the Villainy, take Pride and Comforts at their Deaths in it, ſo far were they from repenting or expreſſing the leaſt Sorrow for it, and yet had Abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution publickly after a very unuſual manner, which plainly ſhews what Thoughts their Confeſſors had of that Matter, for which they died. Bleſſed God! how amazing is it that any that had ever heard of thee, or thy Nature, or Properties, eſpecially that had ever look'd into thoſe Revelations thou haſt made thereof in thy Written Word, ſhould call the Aſſaſſinating the beſt of Princes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volving his Subjects in Blood, Deſtruction of the beſt Church,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101746:7"/>and the over-turning the beſt conſtituted Government in the World, the Murdering their King in cold Blood, and which muſt have been a conſequence the Butchering of many Thouſands of their innocent Fellow-Subjects, the making all that ſurviv'd Slaves to <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Rome,</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting both their Bodies and Minds to the worſt of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannies; How amazing, I ſay, is it that any ſhould call theſe the Cauſes of God, Religion, and the Laws! as if the Blood of Kings ſhed by their own Subjects was an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable Offering to God; as if Religion were promoted by forcing us into the Communion of ſuch a Church as will lock up the Scripture from us; teach us to believe without Reaſon, to Pray without Underſtanding, and give the Worſhip of God to his Creatures; as if our Laws would be ſafe in the hands of ſuch a Guardian, who Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannizes Arbitrarily over his own Subjects, and would have had the pretence of Conqueſt to uſe us worſe if poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: If theſe are the Cauſe of God and Religion, I know no ſuch thing as the Works of the Devil, and what we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounc'd as ſuch in our Baptiſm was a meer <hi>Chimera.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſhews how much the Intereſt of a Party, when a Man's throughly embark'd, can blind his Reaſon as well as harden his Conſcience, how dangerous it is to engage at all in a Faction, ſince a Man knows not where he ſhall ſtop when he is once in, how by ſteps he is lead to call Evil Good, and Good Evil, and practice accordingly, and to make the meaſures of both the ſerviceableneſs or diſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceableneſs of any Action to the Party, and how careful every one that has any regard for his Soul ſhould be, when he chooſeſt out for the directors of his Conſcience, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſts with the Conduct of it.</p>
            <p>But to return, after all this, I ſay 'twould be but to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe your Time and Patience to offer at any other proof of the truth and reality of the wicked Deſign; whoever can call for further Conviction does the leaſt need it; 'tis
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101746:8"/>no breach of Charity to believe, that none can pretend to doubt of it but ſuch as know it too well.</p>
            <p>Let us then briefly ſee, what the Deſign was, and as to that, examine the ſame Particulars which we did in <hi>Iſrael</hi>'s caſe, who were engaged in it, what they intended againſt us, how near they were to effect it, and how ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we eſcap'd it?</p>
            <p>Our Enemies, like theirs, were ſuch <hi>whoſe Wrath was kindled againſt us.</hi> Nothing under God has or does ſo much obſtruct the aſpiring and wicked Deſigns of our Neighbour on the other ſide of the Water, as this Nation and Church; nothing can ſatisfie the Pride and Ambition of that Prince leſs than an univerſal Monarchy, and no Methods does he ſtick at, how baſe and ungrateful, how fraudulent and treacherous, how violent and cruel ſoever, that may promote his great end, no ties of Honour and Conſcience, no Obligations of Juſtice or Mercy, no Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or Leagues, neither Word nor Oath can hold him, but he breaks through them with as much eaſe as <hi>Sampſon</hi> did <hi>the Withs that bound him, which were as a Thread of Tow when it toucheth the Fire.</hi> But while he makes War and diſturbance every where, that he may have quiet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, that if at any time the Wounds he gives his Neighbours ſhould touch his own Conſcience, his Paraſitical Prieſts may pour in their Oil, and ſpeak Peace to him; he, at their inſtigation and direction, muſt attone for theſe Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities by committing others; (as 'tis no new thing for thoſe Confeſſors to enjoin for a Penance the repetition of thoſe Crimes which have been acknowledged in Confeſſion) the Ambition of the univerſal Monarch may be ſerv'd, if at the ſame time care be taken to ſatisfie the Pride of the occumenical Biſhop; and let him uſe the moſt wicked and cruel Methods to enlarge his Dominions, and bring Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries under his Tyranny, they ſhall be forgiven him, if he will do ſo meritorious an act as to put the ſame Methods
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101746:8"/>in practice to extend the Papal Yoke, and bring Hereticks into the Boſom of the Catholick Church.</p>
            <p>And what he has done in order to both theſe ends, is too notorious to need my inſiſting upon it, and does ſufficiently demonſtrate how violent and impetuous thoſe Deſigns are, which are ſuggeſted by Ambition and falſe Zeal; and how eagerly ſuch purſue them as are ſpurr'd on by their own Pride, encourag'd by the blandiſhments, or driven with the laſh of a Confeſſor; and what Indignation then may we imagine will ſuch conceive againſt all thoſe that are obſtacles in their way, break their Meaſures and defeat their Deſigns?</p>
            <p>Time was when <hi>England</hi> was in the Intereſts of <hi>France,</hi> giving her helping hand to the enſlaving the Nations of <hi>Europe,</hi> and her ſelf among the reſt; and not many Years ſince our <hi>Romiſh</hi> Adverſaries had a proſpect likewiſe (at leaſt as they flatter'd themſelves) to have eſtabliſh'd their Antichriſtian Religion here; and indeed, had that unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Alliance continued, had this Nation aſſiſted them, or but ſtood neuter till now, in all probability before this time the Shackles, the wooden Shooes had been on, the Ears of <hi>Europe</hi> had been bored; and had they ſucceeded in their Attempts upon this Church, and by Fraud or Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence deſtroyed her, the great Bulwork of Proteſtancy would have been gone, and the <hi>Northern Hereſie,</hi> as they pleaſe to call it, laid open to be torn up by the Roots.</p>
            <p>But this Kingdom has broke with <hi>France,</hi> and joyned with the other Princes of Chriſtendom, in defending their common Liberties and Rights, and oppoſing that torrent that was over-whelming them all; and we may ſay, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Vanity in our ſelves, or Injuſtice to others, that our Forces in conjunction with theirs, have ſtem'd the Tide, and that the weight of them has turn'd the Ballance; and that juſt Zeal, that Strength and Courage wherewith the Fathers and Sons of this Church encountred the daring
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101746:9"/>Attempts of the Prieſts of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion in the laſt Reign, have given ſuch a foil to that Church, have ſo baffled their Cauſe, expoſed the Weakneſs, as well as Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs of it, that it muſt lie dead as long as the Trophies of their Victory remain, nor can revive till their Enemies can have an opportunity of treating their Books as they would their Perſons, committing both to the Flames, which indeed is the quickeſt and ſureſt way of ſtopping the Mouths of Hereticks, and confuting their Writings: No wonder therefore if they look upon us as their worſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, who have given ſuch a check to the careers of that Monarch, and the deſigns of that Church, and have all the Malice and Rage againſt us, that diſappointment in their greateſt hopes can ſuggeſt.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, we have a Prince who does not more oppoſe the Ambition of that Monarch by his Arms, than he eclipſes his Glory by his Perſonal Character, while He bravely leads his own Troops, and expoſes Himſelf in the hotteſt Action, and gallantly faces Death in a thouſand Shapes: How does He reproach that undue tenderneſs and over care which the other has for his Perſon, who never ventures it within the reach of Danger, or ſight of an Enemy; and while One maintains the glorious Character of a Father of his own Country, and a Friend and Patron to the Neighbouring ones, how little doth it make the Other's Figure, who is a Terror to his Subjects, an Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor of his Neighbours, dreaded at Home, and hated Abroad?</p>
            <p>'Tis not ſtrange then if the <hi>Wrath</hi> of Enemies, to whom we have given ſo great and inſupportable Provocations, be <hi>kindled against us,</hi> and ready to break forth with the greateſt Violence, even to the conſuming of us, if their Power be equal to it: And ſo indeed it had like to have done.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:101746:9"/>
            <p>For the miſchief they intended, and were ready to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute, was no leſs than the Murdering our King, and the invading the Kingdom in the diſtraction that that ſad occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion would have put us in; 'Tis more than probable; that that cautious Monarch who never had the Courage to meet his glorious Enemy in the Field, laid, or was privy to the Deſign of taking him off after ſuch a baſe and barbar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner: The dying Criminals that were ſo careful to clear many others from being acceſſary to it, ſay nothing to acquit him, and indeed it is not to be imagined that men would of their own heads have engaged in ſo black and hazardous an Enterprize; for which if they had ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded in it he muſt have ſacrificed them to his honour he would have been bound in Prudence and Policy to have waſh'd his hands of the blood of the Murdered King in theirs that ſhed it, 'tis not, I ſay, to be believed, that any would have engaged in ſuch an undertaking upon ſuch terms unleſs they had ſome previous aſſurance from him that could give it them, not only of impunity but reward: And if he had not deſign'd the Aſſaſſination, as a Preli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary, not only expedient for the facilitating his intended Invaſion, but indeed as abſolutely neceſſary in order to the ſucceſs of it, why upon the diſcovery and prevention of that has he deſiſted from this? However that were, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent number of hardned Villains (much ſuch a number as bound themſelves with an Oath to kill St. <hi>Paul</hi>) were ready for the deſign, Horſes and Arms provided, and the place pitch'd upon, each had their Poſt aſſign'd them, and they waited for nothing but an account of the King's go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abroad to put it in Execution. If the blow had been given, what a ſurprize, what a conſternation would this Kingdom have been in; if our Shepherd had been Smitten how ſhould we have been Scattered like a flock of ſilly helpleſs Sheep? our head would have been gone, and our hearts failed us, we ſhould have had neither Counſel nor Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to have oppoſed thoſe Forces that were at that time to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101746:10"/>Land upon us, but muſt have fallen an eaſy pray to them: Reflect a little my Brethren, (if you dare) what would have been the dreadful conſequences if this deſign had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken effect. One cannot without horror think upon a French Army, waſting our country, burning our Towns and Houſes, butchering our Friends and Relations; what com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort could any one have taken that ſhould have eſcaped with his Life, to ſee a plentiful Country turned into a barren Wilderneſs, a free People that had many valuable rights made Slaves and dependants upon the Arbitrary Will of a Tyrannical Conquerour; a pure Religion extir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pated, and Idolatry and Superſtition ſet up in the room of it?</p>
            <p>This muſt have been the miſerable condition in which we ſhould all have been involved: If any think they ſhould have fared better than their Neighbours upon the account of their own great Merits on the fair promiſes they may have had from abroad, they have very wrong notions of Popiſh Gratitude, and French Truſt, Alas Papiſts have engroſs'd all merit, there is no ſuch thing in Proteſtants, and Promiſes made to the prejudice of the great Monarch, or Holy Church, are not to be kept. All they could have hoped for, is, that if they would have gone ſome few ſteps further, and turn'd their Religion, they might poſſibly have been treated as the new Converts are in <hi>France,</hi> but otherwiſe all the mercy to have been expected would have been this, to have been eaten laſt, though it has not always been ſo, inſtances are not wanting where thoſe Proteſtants that have been moſt zealous and forward in ſetting up a Popiſh Prince have been the firſt that had cauſe to repent of it.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, whatever is dear to us as men, Engliſh Men, and Proteſtants, muſt have been wreſted from us, 'tis not to be ſuppoſed that being driven on by Rage and Revenge, as well as Avarice and Ambition, they ſhould have uſed ſofter methods here than they do in their other Conqueſts, where they tinge the Rivers with Blood, where Sword
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101746:10"/>and Fire devour all before them, and if they would but totally extirpate the rational Inhabitants of the Country and leave none but the four footed ones of the Field and Foreſt, the Beaſts of burthen, the Beaſts of prey they would make very proper Subjects for ſuch a Government.</p>
            <p>But though God ſuffered them to go ſo far as they did in their Helliſh Enterprize, that the proof of it might be clear beyond denial, or doubt, yet was he pleas'd ſo ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably to diſcover and defeat it, that the miſchief falls on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on their heads that deviſed it, and we may ſay with <hi>Iſrael, he has not given us as a prey to their teeth, our Soul is eſcaped as a Bird out of the Snare of the Fowler, the Snare is broken, and we are eſcaped:</hi> with them let us alſo join in making ſuch grateful returns to the Divine Goodneſs as the great Mercy calls for.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Let us look up to God as the Author of it: I do acknowledge it is not always ſafe or eaſy to determine what events are to be aſcribed to God's ſpecial efficacious Providence, and as the Lords doing, and what are not; yet in ſome there are ſuch viſible marks of Diſcrimination, that a Man muſt be willfully blind if he does not diſtinguiſh them. I may not at preſent enter upon this Argument, and ſhall only ſay that in occurrances which are brought about unexpectedly, but ſeaſonably for the deliverance or good of a Church, or Nation, profeſſing God's true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, without their privity or aſſiſtance, by inviſible, or incompetent means, or by the Miniſtry or Inſtrumentality of ſuch things as are only, or immediately under the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and government of God, in ſuch caſes not to trace the out-goings of the Almighty where his footſteps are ſo plain, is to be more ſtupid, or Atheiſtical than the very Heathens: <hi>Pſ.</hi> 126.2. <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.25.</p>
            <p>In our deliverance I will remark but two things which muſt lead us to God as the Author of it: The deſign againſt the King's Life was prevented only by the diſcovery vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily made by ſome of thoſe who were to be concern'd
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:101746:11"/>in the execution of it; and the Invaſion or Deſcent upon us was hindred by our Fleets being in ſuch a readineſs to guard our own Coaſts and block up our Enemies in their Harbours.</p>
            <p>But to what ſhall we aſcribe all this, was it through our Policy or Conduct that we had ſuch a Fleet at home? Were they not to have been gone long before to the <hi>Streights</hi> and ſtopt only by a contrary ſtrange Wind which has hardly been known at that Seaſon of the Year to ſit ſo long in that quarter? And to whom ſhall we attribute this, but to him <hi>whom the Wind and Seas obey, who brings the Winds out of his Treaſures,</hi> and makes them <hi>blow under Heaven whither he liſts?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And what was it that made the diſcoverers confeſs the deſigned Aſſaſſination, when 't was ſo near being Executed. were they not Papiſts, who are not generally over tender of the Blood and lives of Hereticks, when their deſtruction may promote the good of Holy Church, were they not engaged and encouraged in it by ſome of their Prieſts, and no doubt aſſured if they loſt their lives in the attempt, of Eternal Life in Exchange; and how came the Chriſtian, the Gentleman, the Man to be too hard for the Papiſts, Conſcience, Honour, or Pity to be too ſtrong for their Religion, what, or who touch'd their hearts, and melted them into remorſe and Confeſſion? Who but he who only knows, and alone can change the heart, take away the heart of ſtone, and give one of fleſh? Him therefore let us acknowledge to be our Saviour and Deliverer, and ſay <hi>if the Lord himſelf had not been on our ſide when men roſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us they had ſwallowed us up quick, when they were ſo wrathfully diſpleaſed at us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. To him let us in the ſecond place pay the tribute of praiſe and thanks for it, this is what he expects, <hi>call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me in the day of trouble and I will hear thee and thou ſhalt praiſe me:</hi> And very reaſonable certainly, for any benefit beſtowed brings the perſon that receives it into debt to his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101746:11"/>Benefactor, and thanks is the leaſt part of payment if God has reſcued us from the very Jaws of Death how ought we to glorify him both in Soul and Body which he has redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. How ſhould we excite all the powers of our Soul and Members of our Bodies to join in his praiſe? <hi>Praiſe the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me bleſs his holy name who ſaveth thy life from deſtruction and crowneth thee with mercy and loving kindneſs. Awake alſo my Glory, my tongue ſhall ſpeak of thy righteouſneſs, O Lord, and my Lips ſhall praiſe thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Has he preſerved to us our Churches where we may have liberty to worſhip him in Purity and the beauty of Holineſs; has he ſecured to us thoſe <hi>ſwept and garniſht Houſes from the return of the evil ſpirit, and ſhall not the Tribes go up thither to worſhip, to give thanks to his holy name?</hi> Has he continued to us a ſervice in our own Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, and ſhall we not join in it when we may <hi>ſing with the Spirit, and with the underſtanding alſo; and can ſay</hi> Amen <hi>at the giving of thanks?</hi> Have we ſtill acceſs to him through the Mediation and Interceſſion of our <hi>great High Prieſt</hi> only, and ſhall we not <hi>through him offer to God the Sacrifice of praiſe continually?</hi> May we ſtill partake of the Wine as well as Bread in the Euchariſt, and ſhall we <hi>not receive the Cup of Salvation, and call upon the name of the Lord?</hi> Is <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſafe notwithſtanding her Enemies <hi>cry'd down with her, down with her, even to the ground, and may our Feet ſtand in her Gates;</hi> may we yet frequent her ſolemn Aſſembly, and praiſe the Lord of Heaven with Muſick Vocal and Inſtrumental? and ſhall we be ſilent? If any thing ſtrikes us dumb but wonder and aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at the greatneſs and ſtrangeneſs of our Salvation, we ſhall deſerve to continue ſo, and that <hi>our tongues ſhould cleave to the roof of our mouths;</hi> 'tis fit the neglected <hi>Harps ſhould be hang'd for ever upon the Willows,</hi> and the skilful <hi>hand</hi> that toucht them <hi>forget its cunning,</hi> if they make not <hi>a chearful noiſe to the God of</hi> Jacob upon ſo Joyful an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101746:12"/>and <hi>if we prefer not</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>above our chief Joy,</hi> and join not <hi>in one of the Songs of Zion</hi> for her deliverance in the Temple of God, how deſervedly may God give her up to the will of our Enemies, ſuffer them to carry us away Captive, and tauntingly <hi>require of us in a ſtrange Land, a Song and Melody in our heavineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Brethren, this is the buſineſs for which Authority has this Day call'd us together, and who ever can will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully diſobey that call, and without very juſt reaſon refuſe to come up with <hi>the multitude to the Houſe of God, with the Voice of Joy and Praiſe, with the Multitude that keep Holy-day,</hi> they give but juſt cauſe of ſuſpicion that they were Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſhers to the Villainous Deſign, and are ſorry 'tis defeated. I am very glad to ſee ſuch a numerous appearance in this place, and hope that better Principles than Formality or Curioſity, or fear of Cenſure; that a true ſence of the never to be forgotten Mercy, and hearty deſire to expreſs your thankfulneſs to the gracious Author of it, has brought you together. And oh! that I could ſay any thing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe that ſence in you, and to enlarge your Hearts, and raiſe up your Souls to the higheſt pitch of Gratitude and Devotion.</p>
            <p>Aſſure your ſelves, if the greatneſs of the deſtruction which threatned, and was within few days of over taking us, if the wonderfulneſs of our deliverance, who are <hi>eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped as a Bird that was taken in the Snare,</hi> if the viſible ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of the hand of God in our reſcue, who ſaw the Snares and Deſigns our Enemies were privily laying, while we were ſecure and unapprehenſive of them, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd and broke them before they could take effect; if theſe are any motives of thankfulneſs, they have their full ſtrength and force upon us in the preſent caſe: All that is valuable to us, as appertaining either to this Life or God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, our Lives, with all the Comforts of them, our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties, our Eſtates, our Friends, and which, I hope, we eſteem above all, our Reformed Religion, were all upon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101746:12"/>the very brink of ruine: The Blow was near being given, and we knew nothing of it, ſo far were we from being able to have warded it of, which muſt either have Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered us preſently, or if any had ſurvived it for ſome time they muſt have lived Slaves, and then died with the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable proſpect of leaving their wretched Poſterity ſuch; fetter'd both in Body and Mind, under Temporal and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Chains, and nothing has prevented this Blow, or ſaved us from this ruine, but a merciful and watchful Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence: Let us then ſay in the words of our Royal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God, the God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>who only, doth wondrous things, and bleſſed be his glorious name for ever, and let the whole Earth be filled with his glory,</hi> Amen. Amen.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But laſtly, to conclude, let us repoſe our Truſt and Confidence in this God for the future, and ſay with <hi>Iſrael our help ſtandeth in the name of the Lord who made Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth:</hi> 'Tis certain this Church and Nation have been for ſome time preſerved in that peaceable and happy ſtate we enjoy by little leſs than Miracle; God has as plainly appeared for us as he did of old for his People whom he brought out of <hi>Aegypt with a mighty hand;</hi> but yet as they were queſtioning his power even in the midſt of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, and diſtruſting his goodneſs at the ſame time that they had preſent Experience of it (<hi>He ſmote the ſtony Rock indeed, but can he give bread,</hi> &amp;c.) Thoſe mouths which ſhould have been opened only in his praiſe, were filled with nothing but murmurings and diffidence; ſo has it been with too many among us, complainings and repine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, doubts and deſpair almoſt have been heard in our ſtreets, and how juſtly might God have verifyed our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and unthankful fears? When St. <hi>Peter</hi> at his own requeſt was commanded by Chriſt to come unto him upon the Water, he walked ſafely upon the ſurface of it while his Faith boy'd him up, but when at the raging of the Winds his Faith began to ſhake, and he was afraid, as if Chriſt who he ſaw at that time <hi>Commanded the Seas
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101746:13"/>and they obey'd,</hi> could not govern the Winds too, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him againſt both; how reaſonably did Chriſt chaſtiſe his deſpondency and want of Faith by letting him begin to ſink? And ſo might God have dealt with us, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn his Protection from us, and ſuffered the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to have over-whelmed us, when we had ſo unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily diſtruſted his Power and Readineſs to Rule the raging of them, after he had ſo often forced them within their Banks, and for our ſakes ſaid to them, <hi>hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſhall you come, and no further?</hi> But he has rather choſe to upbraid than correct us for our repining and doubting, and to bring us to our duty of an humble affiance and truſt in him, by giving freſh inſtances of his Power and Goodneſs, than puniſh our neglect of it by withdrawing them from us: How ſhould this even ſhame us out of our inſidelty (I can call it no better) and give us a holy Confidence in him, and Dependance upon him; that he who has ſo often and ſtrangely appeared for us, will be our God and Guide for ever; that he <hi>who has deliver'd us from ſo great a death, and doth deliver, will yet deliver us;</hi> and perfect in his time that good work which he has begun, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on ſo far for us.</p>
            <p>But then in order to this truſt and relyance, that they may be reaſonable and well grounded, we cann't but think there is ſomething to be done by us, and what is that but to endeavour to walk worthy of that goodneſs which God has ſhew'd to us, by improving the mercy, he continues to us to his Glory, and by making him the returns of a filial fear, unfeigned Love, and an univerſal Obedience? without this our Faith will be but a vain Conſidence, and meer Preſumption.</p>
            <p>We have the beſt Government and Laws in the World, but if we are looſe and lawleſs in our Lives, the advantage of our Conſtitution will be ſo far from availing us, that contrariwiſe it will make a conſiderable Article in the charge againſt us; it will both haſten our account and make it the more heavy.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:101746:13"/>
            <p>We have a Prince to go in and out before us, to Rule us at home, and Fight for us abroad, who does at leaſt come up to the Character of any that have ſate upon this, or any other Throne before him; but if we do not approve our ſelves good Subjects of the King of Heaven, our Princes Virtues will not ſecure us, though our wickedneſs may in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure him: The Spirit of God has told us, that <hi>for the Sins of a Nation many are the Princes thereof.</hi> God may as well take away a good one as give a bad King <hi>in his wrath,</hi> and we know he once threatned a People, that if they <hi>did wickedly they ſhould be deſtroyed, both they and their King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We have a pure Religion a Church reformed from the corruptions of that of <hi>Rome,</hi> but if our Converſations are impure and we are unreform'd in our manners, will our Church, or our Faith ſave us? God will indeed have a Church to the end of the World, and <hi>the gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt her,</hi> but ſure he is not tied to this, or that particular Place, or Country, the Goſpel may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from one Kingdom and yet not out of the World, but tranſplanted to another, and our Saviour has plainly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough told us upon what terms he will give, or take it away from a People in thoſe words to the Jews, the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Heaven ſhall be taken from you, and given to a Nation that ſhall bring forth the Fruits thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would we therefore that God ſhould go on to preſerve and ſecure theſe bleſſings to us, and that we may raiſe to our ſelves a ground and conſidence in him that he will, we ſee how we muſt qualify our ſelves for them, we muſt not be barren and unfruitful under all the Cultivations and Husbandry, all the gracious methods which he uſes to improve us, but muſt <hi>bring forth Fruits meet for repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, the bleſſed Fruits of the Spirit, love, joy, peace, long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, gentleneſs, goodneſs, faith, meekneſs, temperance.</hi> Being thus diſpoſed we may reaſonably hope for God's Bleſſing upon our endeavours; 'tis true our endeavours without the divine aſſiſtance will turn to little account, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101746:14"/>'tis certain God can if he pleaſes, ſave us without our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing any thing towards it; but yet, though God may, and does ſometimes for weighty reaſons act either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately, at leaſt without the miniſtry of them, for whoſe ſake he acts and after a very extraordinary manner, yet where there is no ſpecial promiſe, 'tis not to be expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that God ſhould go out of his ordinary methods of his Providence, which is to act by the inſtrumentality of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes to cooperate with the honeſt endeavours of Men, when there is room for them, and make that ſucceſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for their ſupport, or preſervation: And therefore as no ſucceſs is to be expected from our endeavours without the divine aſſiſtance, ſo that aſſiſtance cannot reaſonably be expected without the uſe of our endeavours.</p>
            <p>The Husbandman would be thought very wild and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant in his expectation that ſhould think to reap a plentiful Crop without manuring and tilling his ground, preparing it for and committing the ſeed to it in due man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and ſeaſon, and yet 'tis certain 'tis <hi>God only that can give the increaſe. The Watchman undoubtedly waketh but in vain unleſs the Lord keep the City,</hi> but yet if a Town be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagur'd by an Enemy ſhould neglect to Man their Forts, and guard their Avenues, and inſtead of unanimouſly joining together to defend themſelves and oppoſe the Foe, ſhould quarrel among themſelves and fall a tearing and devouring one another, it would not be hard to gueſs what would be the fate of it. I ſay, our endeavours muſt not be wanting towards our own ſafety, though 'tis only God's Bleſſing upon them that can make them ſucceſsful for that end. That therefore we may expect and receive that bleſſing, let us do our parts, purſue thoſe methods that tend moſt plainly to the ſecuring them, and truſt God with the event.</p>
            <p>Nothing under Heaven but Union and Reſolution can ſecure us; if we are broken into Factions, and purſuing the intereſt of Parties, or private Revenge, while the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101746:14"/>is watching for the ruine of the whole. We may learn from our Saviour what is like to become of us, <hi>a Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf cannot ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If now the Adverſary has ſhew'd himſelf ſo openly and daringly, we ſhall be Cowardly, or to put it into other words, cautious and reſerved; we invite and encourage his attempts upon us: This is no time to diſſemble, we muſt declare plainly one way or other; either reſolve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a brave Defence, or to yield our Necks to the Yoke.</p>
            <p>My Brethren we want no Engagements or Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to unite and to be bold.</p>
            <p>The cauſe we are to unite in, is the Cauſe of our King and Country, and indeed of all <hi>Europe;</hi> 'tis the Cauſe of our Church and the whole Proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>We are not left alone to grapple with our Enemies, we have moſt of the Princes and States of Chriſtendom join'd with us; and which is moſt encouraging of all, hitherto God has appeared for us: Let us then join as one Man, both Heart and Hand, in defence of our ſelves, our little ones, and all our Subſtance (as <hi>Ezra</hi> expreſſes it) in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of our Liberties, our Laws and Religion; and for the ſake of theſe in defence of our King and Government, upon whom, under God, all theſe depend. We have all the ſtricteſt Obligations to him that can be laid upon us, of Gratitude, of Duty, of Intereſt.</p>
            <p>Shall we not unite in the defence of him that has once reſcued us out of the very Jaws of Deſtruction, and is ſtill guarding us with the utmoſt hazards and fatigue, in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of that Precious Life which has been ſo often expoſed for the ſecurity of ours?</p>
            <p>Have we not ſworn many of us, to bear Faith and true Allegiance to him, and do we not all every day beg of God, in our publick Prayers, to ſtrengthen him that he may Vanquiſh and Overcome all his Enemies; and ought we not to convince the World that we have not in our Oaths prevaricated with God as well as impoſed upon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:101746:15"/>Man; that in our Prayers our Hearts do not give the Lye to our Tongues, by our readineſs to make good our Oaths upon ſuch an occaſion, and to ſecond our Prayers by our hearty endeavours? Are we not Embarkt in one Cauſe, have we not the ſame common concern with him, both Civil and Religious? So that to join in his Defence, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed to join in our own: why then ſhould we not reſolve to ſtand by him and one another, with the ſame Courage with which he Fights for us all?</p>
            <p>To conclude, Let us firſt ſeek and engage the Divine Favour and Bleſſing, and then add our joint Endeavours, as our Places and Capacities give us opportunity, for our common Security; and being reconciled to God by Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and newneſs of Life, and united to one another by all the Bonds which our common Relation and Intereſts, as to Nature, Country, and Religion obliges us; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to act in good earneſt for the benefit and ſafety of the whole, we may confidently rely upon God, that he will proſper and give ſucceſs to our Endeavours, that he will guard us at home, <hi>and go forth with our Fleets and Armies, and fight our Battles abroad, that he will preſerve the breath of our Noſtrils; bleſs him in his going out and coming in, give his Angels charge over him, and cover his head in the day of Battel: that he will be a Sun and a Shield to enlighten and protect him, to keep him from the Arrow that flyeth by day, and the evil that walketh in darkneſs; that he will bring him back with Honour and Victory, and Crown at laſt all his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and our Wiſhes with a happy and durable Peace: and that our Enemies being ſcatter'd, who delighted in blood, we being delivered from their hands, may ſerve him without fear, in holyneſs and righteouſneſs, before him, all the days of our Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:101746:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
